Sebastian Bernasek

Data Scientist | Chemical Enginee

San Francisco Bay Area

🛘 🖺 630-624-9699 | 🗷 sbernasek@gmail.com | 🏕 sbernasek.com | 🖸 sebastianbernasek | 🛅 sbernasek

Summary_

Data scientist with proven success in building models to understand and predict the behavior of complex systems, as evidenced by several academic publications and granted patents. Brings a unique blend of scientific literacy, mathematical fluency, engineering pragmatism, and technical creativity, all backed by strong python scripting skills and a healthy dose of common sense. Recently concluded 5 years of academic research preceded by 3 years working at a midstage startup, and is now seeking new opportunities to continue learning while making a difference.

Expertise includes:

- **Developing quantitative models** to analyze and simulate complex processes.
- Empowering decisions with insight backed by rigorous analysis.
- Building rich data sets by turning qualitative observations into quantitative measurements.
- Hacking together data-driven solutions to a wide variety of everyday problems.
- Identifying and prototyping state of the art methods derived from the research literature.
- Bridging the gap between research, engineering, and business by emphasizing the broader implications of technical nuances.

Skills

Data Engineering Analysis Computer Vision Modeling Coding Feature extraction Python & Cython Relational databases Hypothesis testing Stochastic processes Package development Web scraping Bayesian inference Image segmentation Dynamical systems NLP, Structured text, RegEx Unsupervised learning Nonlinear regression **REST APIs** Feature classification Feature selection Networks & Time series Spatial analysis Classification Git, LaTeX, HTML/CSS Dimensionality reduction Visualization Quantitative microscopy Agent-based models Unix shell, OSX/Ubuntu

Education

Ph.D. in Chemical and Biological Engineering Northwestern University

2014 - 2019

• Dissertation combined data science and chemical engineering to explore how cells make reliable decisions.

B.S. in Chemical Engineering • High Honors University of California, Santa Barbara

2008 - 2012

• Exchange student at Imperial College London throughout 2010/2011.

Experience_

Personal Development & Consulting

Present

Took a year off to explore the world, assisting some friends along the way:

- Built a database of 5k+ targeted B2B sales leads using a combination of web-scraping, commercial APIs, and machine learning.
- Provided data-driven insight that enabled a recruiting firm to boost their monthly revenue by focusing on more probable hires.
- Automated several text content extraction and parsing routines to save hundreds of hours of tedious labor.

Researcher at Northwestern University Evanston, IL

2014 - 2019

- Published in high profile journals including Cell and PLOS Computational Biology.
- Designed, built, and deployed several simulation and analysis frameworks for the broader research community.
- Discovered a surprising link between expression dynamics and metabolism by developing a model that accurately predicts developmental mistakes.
- · Discovered a novel cell decision mechanism by using computer vision and statistical analysis to derive insight from microscopy data.
- · Increased data volume and quality by developing a computer vision pipeline for automated analysis of microscope images.

Process Engineer at LanzaTech Chicago, IL

2012 - 2014

- · Developed innovative renewable energy design concepts, earning two granted patents and further pending applications.
- · Designed and built the company's core process modeling framework, which was rapidly adopted by all engineers.
- Collaborated with external technology providers to identify complementary value streams, leading to formal corporate partnerships.
- Modeled refinery-scale processes to predict and optimize economic and life-cycle performance.
- · Advised executives and investors with technical analysis that directly inspired major strategic decisions.

Research Assistant at UC Santa Barbara Santa Barbara, CA

2011 - 2012

• Conducted first ever dynamic measurement of interaction forces between vesicles. Published in Soft Matter